Downloaded @ subs4free.club
WITH THE SUPPORT OF THE AQUITAINE
LIMOUSIN POITOU-CHARENTES REGION
THE COUNTY OF THE LOIRE REGION
AND THE COUNTY COUNCIL OF DORDOGNE
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE CNC
AND CATALA INSTITUTE
OF THE CULTURAL EMPRESSES
WITH THE PARTICIPATION
OF ARTE COFINOVA 12, DE CINE +
AND CATALUNYA TELEVISION
Go ahead.
THE DEATH OF LOUIS XIV
Sire,
shall we join our guests?
I'd love to, but I cannot.
Oh my dogs-~
My beloved dogs.
It's been 20 days since you saw them.
Yes.
Oh yes...
My dogs...
My dogs
love me.
Yes, Sire,
you are their master.
It's a pity that Dr. Fagon stops me
from seeing them more often.
My dogs...
My dogs that I love so much.
They are splendid.
Sire,
the dogs will return for the night.
Sire?
Would you do us the honour
of coming with us?
Please, Sire.
No no, I'd prefer to go to bed.
It would make us so happy.
Then lwill salute those
who want to see me.
Sire.
Bring me the hat.
Very well, Sire.
Thank you, Sire, bravo.
Blouin.
Sire?
Take the hat away.
Perhaps...
We can try that.
Look at me, Sire.
Yes, good.
Let's try this one.
Donkey milk is the correct remedy.
Your Majesty, we agree.
Fagon?
Your Majesty.
Have you examined
the Marchesa of Cujas?
Yes, Majesty.
It was something I...
Was she beautiful naked?
Beautiful indeed, Majesty.
I think nature was very generous.
To her!
To her, yes.
Fagon keeps us informed about
"everything".
You mean to speak of Mr. Blouin
who has ears and eyes...
all along the palace corridors.
I agree.
It's not the least
of his qualities.
Thank you, doctor.
It's true that...
the Marchesa of Saxony...
if you don't mind me saying, Sire...
is very beautiful.
She's a little more discrete
than the Marchesa of Cujas.
Marchesa of Cujas is not...
How can I say?
Being evidently respectful,
she is not very shy.
The Marchesa of Saxony
is a little more difficult.
But...
If you allow me again, Sire,
these are...
Delightful gardens to play in, Majesty.
Sirs, you may take your leave.
Very well.
Sire, your health is good.
The ladies will be delighted
about your return, Majesty.
He seems much better.
Here are the eggs for your dinner.
Go ahead.
Bravo, Sire.
Would you like some biscotin?
Very well.
Yes.
It's wonderful, Sire...
to see you have your appetite back.
And that you will soon gain strength.
Believe me, this news...
will be received with greatjoy
both within the Kingdom and abroad.
Oh yes, Sire, with greatjoy.
Bravo, Sire.
Look, Sire.
We made a bigger one here...
I asked the Duke of York,
an expert on coastal defences.
He'll explain better than me.
The bridge in La Roche...
The bridge itself is very big
but the entrance is small.
It's a lot easier to protect the bridge
if we make a fortress
on both sides of it.
We need to strengthen...
the soil.
But I'll use a new stone
from the Nile.
We need the money
in advance for the transport
to reduce expenses.
And that is very important
to earn the trust
of the people...
And also the people
we're buying from.
It is very important
to have your approval...
for the advance payment,
so we can begin.
You see how well
the Duke of York worked.
Yes, there's work to do.
Is it really necessary?
Yes, Sire.
The Duke of York
found different cheap stones
from the Nile.
They are more resistant.
Only the transport is more expensive,
which is why we need more money.
I'll think about it, thank you.
Very well.
Lords...
Please excuse me but
I really have to speak with His Majesty.
Sire.
Your Majesty appears
to be most discomforted.
Probably because of the horrible night.
You didn't touch your dessert, Sire.
Water.
Water!
My valet, my valet!
MY Valet!
Sire,
what would you like?
You aren't my valet,
I want water!
Water!
Sire...
Not in that glass...
In a crystal glass.
In a crystal glass!
No, in a crystal glass!
Water! Quickly! Water!
Water!
CIemence!
Clemence, my valet!
My valet.
No, no, no, not you.
CIemence!
Leave me alone!
I had a horrible night.
I had horrible pains
in my left leg.
I don't know
if I can stay upright in Mass.
Pardon me, Majesty, but...
Are you...
sure it's your leg hurting?
Are you sure it's not...
below the kidney?
Well.
In any case, it's better, Sire,
if you hear Mass
from your bed this morning.
No, no,
I prefer to go to the chapel.
Of course, Your Majesty.
Apologies.
Sire.
Allow us, Majesty.
Carefully, Majesty.
Let me know
when you've decided to treat me.
Yes, Sire.
May I, Majesty?
Majesty, could I?
Escort the King to the chapel.
It would have been better
if His Majesty rested.
All this rabbit...
this feeding,
overripe fruit,
meat,
these excesses of sugar,
they are not good for his health.
All these melons,
these blackberries, these figs,
all with cold ice.
Ice preserves.
It's a conservation method.
Which has existed for a long time.
It's proven to work.
But...
Your comments
make me wonder.
I think about
the King's diet a lot.
"Maybe" you should think
more seriously.
I don't have to justify myself to you
or any other valet.
Perhaps...
In fact,
something different more often,
every day---
It would be better.
We don't lack fruit or vegetables
in our gardens.
May |?
This grape is exquisite.
What about
BIouin's suggestion?
To bring doctors in
from the university?
I don't approve it.
Why?
These men...
Are doctors in classrooms.
They look after books.
And an audience.
I've rarely seen them care for the sick.
Mr. Fagon.
These are doctors from the Sorbonne.
It has a great reputation, as you know.
I think that the reputation
of the doctors of the Faculty,
Mr. de Moliere
has described it perfectly.
They are even more dangerous
as a group-
Mr. Fagon.
I don't think now is the time
to search for Moliere...
What I wish for is answers.
You know as well as me
that medicine is not an exact science
that gives you answers as you please.
But, this business of feeding
is a lead to follow.
I will see to this.
Please, excuse me, Sire.
You need to get up
to stretch your limbs.
Careful, Sire.
Take your time.
No?
Let's not push.
Sit and rest like this
for a moment, Sire.
Very well.
Excuse us, Sire,
I wanted to talk with...
Mr. Blouin and Mr. Marechal.
There is an important meeting at 4pm
with the ministers.
It must be cancelled.
His Majesty wants to be there,
as you know.
Of course,
but his health is more important.
I will try to change his mind.
Go and tell him.
It's beyond my control.
Sire.
The doctors want the meeting
at 4pm to be cancelled.
And that we tell this to Mr. Pelletier.
Please, excuse me, Sire.
But I think you should stay in bed.
I will bandage Your Majesty's leg.
— You need bandages.
-And ointment, Mr. Blouin.
Your Majesty.
That's a relief!
I'm so glad, Your Majesty.
Put it everywhere, it's important.
A little more, Majesty.
Lift your leg a little, Majesty.
Can you hold it like that, Blouin?
Thank you.
Wait a little longer, Majesty.
Mr. Marechal has nearly finished
bandaging your leg.
It's finished, Majesty.
Careful.
Fagon, help us.
Cover it.
Perfect. Now you can rest, Sire.
Your Majesty.
Sire?
Are you sure
you want to meet the ministers now?
I have to go
to the Council of Ministers.
All that can wait.
It's my duty.
We can do that later...
My leg isn't hurting me anymore.
Bring me my wheelchair.
It's intelligence that counts!
Bring me my wheelchair, please.
Valet!
More water.
I must tell you, Sire.
You are misusing your strength.
It would be preferable
you would lie and rest.
You should take me back to bed.
Mr. Fagon?
Don't you think...
the bird's presence
is hindering the King's convalescence?
No.
I don't see how the bird
would stop the King from getting better.
My mother
always told me
that birds carry disease.
This bird is in a cage.
It has no contact with the King.
Sickness can cross bars, Mr. Fagon.
Obviously
you are a great scholar in Medicine.
I remind you that earlier...
you insisted that
His Majesty's dogs
could enter his room.
And now...
you want to take away a little bird.
Your logic escapes me,
Mr. Blouin.
I'm just a little worried.
We all are, Mr. Blouin.
But at the moment you will allow
to make it so that things stay
as they are.
Mr. Fagon?
Mr. Blouin,
you're having trouble falling asleep?
Have you heard about
a Dr. Lebrun?
Dr. Lebrun?
The one from Marseilles?
He's from Marseilles, yes.
I've heard about a Dr. Lebrun
of Marseilles from some...
friends.
Doctor friends.
But that's all I know.
Why are you talking
about this Dr. Lebrun?
He was introduced to the court.
I know nothing about him.
We haven't even invited
the Sorbonne doctors yet,
and a doctor from Marseilles
is already coming?
And also very controversial,
if I believe my friends.
I'm just amazed that you can have faith
in such oId—fashioned beliefs.
That's all.
They are not beliefs.
And certainly not superstitions
from the Middle Ages.
Believe those who know medicine.
I won't question your habits,
your dispositions.
Please don't mistrust my prerogatives.
Water!
Please!
Water! Water!
Water...
Mr. Blouin, I already told you
not to give in to all his whims.
Leave the King alone please.
You won't lose your leg, Majesty.
I've seen many cases
with such marks.
— None of them were gangrene.
— It's true.
This mark will disappear quickly.
Thank you, Marechal.
The pain has gone.
Sire?
The doctors from the Sorbonne are here.
His Majesty seems
to be suffering from fever.
Majesty, please allow me
to open your mouth.
The tongue, Sire!
His mouth is unusually dry.
Bring him pure water.
Drink this, Sire.
These marks are worrisome.
Worrisome, worrisome.
We'll do everything we can, Sire.
He should probably be bled.
Even if he doesn't like it.
It will make his head spin.
I think we should let His Majesty sleep.
Are those the drums
and the oboes of Saint-Louis‘ day?
Yes, Sire!
Here's your dinner, Sire.
I can't swallow anymore.
Everything revolts me.
Would you like some broth?
Perhaps a little,
but properly strained.
I can't swallow anything.
Very well, Sire.
Everything disgusts me.
- Blouin?
- Yes, Madame?
The Italian musicians,
who'll play at the grand dinner...
The King is here.
Can we ask them to his room?
Of course, Madame.
This leg!
It stinks!
I want to vomit!
I feel nauseated.
My child...
You will be a great king.
Don't imitate me in what concerns
the love for the buildings.
Nor the love I had for the war.
Instead,
make peace with your neighbours.
Give back to God what you owe Him.
Make your people devoted to Him.
Try to console them.
Sire?
Go and fetch Marechal.
Fagon, help me to lift the leg.
Gently.
Breathe, Sire, breathe.
Gangrene...
Cut it off!
Sire, do not be afflicted
of a vain mutilation.
Would you like to drink a bit, Majesty?
You must think of something quickly.
We can't let him suffer like this.
Nothing can be done.
Have you told Father Le Tellier?
Of course.
Stay calm, Majesty.
Do you want to confess, Sire?
Talk to me.
God forgive me...
Bless me...
Bless me.
The Duke of Orleans
told me to come.
You should know
I think you are just a charlatan.
I came to save the King.
I was coming from Marseilles
and while arriving in Paris,
I heard about the King's disease.
I have the elixir to save him.
What is it made of?
It has bull's sperm
and bull's blood
and frog fat.
But we didn't put, this time
for the King,
brain's juice that the English distil.
Trust me.
Perhaps you could demonstrate,
before giving His Majesty the elixir.
Give him water.
To Life
or to Death.
It will save the King.
Who are your teachers?
Give him Alicante wine.
May I?
You haven't replied to my question.
Sir, I would like to know
your masters in the matter of Medicine.
Who taught you what you know?
Give the wine!
Do you want to try again?
It doesn't have any effect.
His Majesty has refused the elixir.
Yes, His Majesty
is getting better.
His gaze is arrested.
He already has...
the sunrise...
the dawn...
the beauty...
and the youth...
Perhaps a bit more elixir?
Yes.
We shouldn't lose hope.
Go...
and get wine and the elixir.
Perhaps we are on the right track.
His expression is more livelier.
And the wine?
I don't really understand
your position on this.
The depths of the earth...
We deal with the physical.
With the bodies of men.
Their guts, like my colleague said.
Yes, but your feet are on the ground.
And from the ground
will grow
the trees,
and plants,
that bloom, and we pick them,
and they come directly
from the depths of earth.
So, there must be a communion.
After all, that is what you preach.
A communion between
the earth and the body.
It's all quite hazy...
Who cured the King from smallpox?
Was it an elixir?
No, it was the doctors,
it was our knowledge, very simply.
The King has had diseases
his whole life, and every time...
He recovered.
Thanks to who?
The Faculty and our skills.
Of instruments.
What do you work with?
Smallpox is like roses,
when they blossom
in spring they are happy.
It's not a rose, sir!
During winter they're sad...
You seem to consider disease
to be a sublimation...
of the body?
Like you have to bear it
to go higher...
We're no longer in the times of Valois,
when one had to suffer...
to meet our Lord.
But what is love?
Love is pain.
Like Arnau de Vilanova explained
in his unquestionable book
"On the Physiology of Love",
love manifests itself
because the picture of the beloved
remains blocked between the eyes.
The picture remains blocked
between the eyes,
due to the temperature of the body,
waters in the brain evaporate
and the brain remains dry.
So let's trepan, if the brain is dry...
We make an incision,
take out the liquids,
put everything back in motion
by mechanical means, sir.
Tools.
Right, because, sir...
bears, stars,
everything you mentioned.
The smallpox, the roses...
That's not enough anymore.
You're an impostor.
I'm starting to think the same.
Have you reflected, Sire,
about the works of the Duke of York?
The fortresses in the West?
We can trust him,
he's a friend of the Kingdom.
Our engineers examined his plans.
They are outstanding.
But the funds
have not been freed up.
We need more money.
Here is your soup, Sire.
You must eat, Sire.
You asked for the Cardinal of Rohan.
Sire.
Monsignor,
I am glad to see you.
I had a sort of dizzy spell.
And I thought I was going to die.
I know it's not good to die,
without the sacraments
of the Church.
But my hour has not come.
I thank you for coming.
Excuse me, Monsignor.
Sire.
You've made the right decision.
It's not time for the last rites.
Sire.
Sire...
Which coffer?
The coffer...
That of my father the King.
And the black one.
The gold coffer and his father's one.
I think his father's one first.
His father's one and the gold one.
Here, Sire.
The last one, Sire.
Thank you, Chancellor.
I'm sorry, Majesty,
but I just burnt my fingers.
Father Le Tellier, Sire.
Sire,
you called for me.
Do you have news
from the Cardinal of Noailles?
No, Sire.
But I am sure
he will answer your invite
and he will come by your side
sooner than scheduled.
He didn't reply to the letter?
He hasn't replied to the letter yet.
Won't he come?
I think he'll come.
Perhaps we need to wait a bit.
But I think he will come.
And you, Blouin?
Have you heard something?
You know it's a delicate question.
But if you wish,
I can obtain more information.
The blood of Christ...
Father, please receive the
body of Christ.
Mr. Blouin,
please receive the body of Christ.
Majesty-
Sire.
Biscotin.
And wine from Alicante.
Where is Madame de Maintenon?
Sire, she went to get the girls
at the Saint-Cyr boarding school,
whose care she is in charge of
and whom she's greatly attached to.
Bring her here.
Sire.
When I die,
you will send my heart
to the professed house of the Jesuits.
And I shall get it mummified,
like my late father, the King.
I'll do what you say, Sire.
I would like
a hot/—cold
Pot of poultry.
The choice of a hot-/cold pot of poultry
may seem strange, but
it's good news.
He's getting his strength back.
If that's what he desires.
If the leg had gone,
the rest of the body would
no longer depart.
It was the best solution,
his leg should have been cut off.
Indeed. It would have
made things easier.
Fagon,
the leg is lost
I think we are at the point
of no return.
Sire?
The doctors want to speak to you.
I'm sorry to trouble your rest,
but we have an important request.
We noticed
that...
Mr. Lebrun's remedy
was far from helping His Majesty
and seems to have worsened
his situation.
Sire?
We must arrest him.
Your Majesty
has shown again exceptional justice.
This was in fact the purpose
of our initiative,
from Mr. Marechal and myself.
We want these...
nasty characters,
to be stripped
of their power to harm.
We hope...
that...
they will be arrested
and sent to the Bastille.
He's an impostor.
Exactly, Sire.
Very dangerous, Sire.
We must arrest him.
We thank His Majesty
for accepting our request.
Allow us to withdraw,
so that you may...
sleep.
Sire.
Through this holy unction,
and His most tender mercy,
may the Lord forgive
your sins.
Sins of the eyes.
Sins of the mouth and the word.
Sins of the ears.
Sins of taste and mouth.
Sins
of touch.
Your hand, Sire.
Go in peace, Sire.
Please stay with the King,
watch over him.
At least drink a little water, Sire.
Pure water.
Pardon me, Sire.
Nothing will help.
We haven't tried the jelly yet.
It all seems so ludicrous.
Sire.
Delicious jelly prepared by your cooks.
No.
Excuse me, Sire.
Let's stop there, Fagon.
Perhaps later...
Pardon me, Sire.
You must eat something.
Just a little bit.
Thank you, sir.
Your Majesty.
Fruit, perhaps.
Please, Sire.
A bit early.
Your Majesty.
Please, open your mouth a little.
I'm sorry for insisting, Your Majesty.
Majesty-
I'm sorry, Majesty,
I was unable to prevent the sickness.
The King is dead.
It's noted, Mr. Fagon.
Write it down.
Go ahead, sirs.
It's a good size...
It's the double of a normal one.
Here is the spleen.
Here...
An inflammation.
We can tell.
So you see that the stomach
was also affected by the gangrene.
Indeed, sir.
I shouldn't have listened
to the birds of ill omen.
I suppose because of the sweat.
Sweat?
Sweat.
He sweated too much.
What is the cause of the gangrene?
I don't know.
You don't know?
We have to open to see the brain.
We'll do that later.
I admit, I didn't believe
it was gangrene.
That is my fault.
You did what you could, Fagon.
Of course.
Gentlemen, we'll do better next time.